Inventory of the Huang Jie diaries
Hoover Institution Archives
Huang Jie diaries
1952-1984
2012C1
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes (2.9 linear feet)
Diaries of Huang Jie, a general in the Chinese Nationalist Army and governor of Taiwan Province, relating to political conditions and military policy in Taiwan.
Huang, Jie, 1902-1995.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Huang Jie was born in Changsha, Hunan Province. In 1924, he entered the Whampoa Military Academy, becoming one of Chiang Kai-shek's best students and most trusted military subordinate, participating in the Northern Expedition (1926-1928), the Chinese civil war of 1930, the great war between China and Japan (1933), the Sino-Japanese War (1937-1945), and the Burma Campaign (1945).
In the summer of 1949, as the Chinese Nationalist Party (the Kuomintang) was on the verge of collapse on the mainland, Huang Jie led thirty thousand Nationalist Chinese Army soldiers in retreat from Hunan Province into Vietnam via Southwest China. After entering Vietnam, they were interned by the French authorities and later stationed at Phu Quoc Island. The army moved to Taiwan in June 1953.
Huang Jie was appointed to several crucial military positions after moving to Taiwan, including garrison commander of Taipei (1953-1954), commander-in-chief of the Nationalist Ground Forces (1954-1957), presidential chief of staff (1957-1958), and Taiwan garrison commander (1958-1962). Huang was governor of Taiwan Province from 1962 to 1969 and minister of defense from 1969 to 1972. He died in Taipei in 1995 at the age of ninety-three.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Huang Jie diaries, relating to political conditions and military policy in Taiwan. provide a rare glimpse into the inner politics of modern Taiwan. They cover the years 1952 to 1956, 1958, 1967 to 1971, and 1973 to 1984.
Taiwan--Politics and government.; Taiwan--Defenses.
- 1952 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- 1953 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- 1954 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- 1955 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- 1956 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- 1958 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- 1967 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- 1968 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- 1969 January-June (Box-folder 2: 5)
- 1969 July-December (Box-folder 3: 1)
- 1970 January-April (Box-folder 3: 2)
- 1970 May-August (Box-folder 3: 3)
- 1970 September-December (Box-folder 3: 4)
- 1971 January-April (Box-folder 3: 5)
- 1971 May-August (Box-folder 3: 6)
- 1973 (Box-folder 4: 1)
- 1974 (Box-folder 4: 2)
- 1975 (Box-folder 4: 3)
- 1976 (Box-folder 5: 1)
- 1977 (Box-folder 5: 2)
- 1978 (Box-folder 5: 3)
- 1979 (Box-folder 6: 1)
- 1980 (Box-folder 6: 2)
- 1981 (Box-folder 6: 3)
- 1982 (Box-folder 6: 4)
- 1983 (Box-folder 7: 1)
- 1984 (Box-folder 7: 2)